Association on American Indian Affairs Records, 1851-2016 (bulk 1922-1995): Finding Aid MC147
Public Policy Papers
- Series 2: Subject Files, 1851-1995; 332 boxes
  - Subseries 1: General, 1868-1995; 116 boxes
    - Reed, Robert E, 1969-1970; 1 folder (Box 154, Folder 5)
    - Region IX American Indian Council, 1973; 1 folder (Box 154, Folder 6)
    - Reifel, Ben, 1951-1960; 1 folder (Box 154, Folder 7)
    - Religious Issues, 1960-1995; 3 folders (Box 154, Folder 8-10)
    - Relocation Program, 1952-1956; 1 folder (Box 154, Folder 11)
    - Relocation Program, 1956-1960; 4 folders (Box 155, Folder 1-4)
    - Republican American Indian Advisory Group, 1952; 1 folder (Box 155, Folder 5)
    - Resnick, Idrian N, 1985-1986; 1 folder (Box 155, Folder 6)
    - Resources for the Future, 1954-1957; 1 folder (Box 155, Folder 7)
    - Revenaugh, Mickey, 1978-1986; 1 folder (Box 155, Folder 8)
    - Revenue Sharing, 1972-1977; 1 folder (Box 155, Folder 9)
    - Revey, James Lone Bear, 1949-1957; 1 folder (Box 155, Folder 10)
    - Rhoades, Everett R, 1970-1985; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 1)
    - Richardson Foundation, 1963; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 2)
    - Rights-of-Way Regulations, 1967-1978; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 3)
    - Riley, Barbara L, 1983-1989; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 4)
    - Rio Grande, 1937-1944; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 5)
    - Risling, David, Jr, 1968-1993; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 6)
    - Ritchie, Andrew, 1973-1974; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 7)
    - Riverside Church, 1979-1987; 2 folders (Box 156, Folder 8-9)
    - RJ Associates, 1975; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 10)
    - RJR Nabisco, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 11)
    - Roads, 1972; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 12)
    - Robert F. Kennedy Memorial, 1968-1983; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 13)
    - Robert Marshall Civil Liberties Trust, 1958-1962; 1 folder (Box 156, Folder 14)
    - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, 1989-1994; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 1)
    - Robinson, Rose W, 1991; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 2)
    - Rockefeller Grants, 1951-1981; 3 folders (Box 157, Folder 3-5)
    - Rockland Community College, 1971-1973; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 6)
    - Rodham, Hillary, 1973-1974; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 7)
    - Roemer, Mildred, 1951-1958; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 8)
    - Rogers, Cornelia B, 1956; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 9)
    - Rogers, Maria, 1938-1943; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 10)
    - Rogers, Will, Jr, 1948-1954; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 11)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1951-1963; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 12)
    - Rose, Ruth Starr, 1960; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 13)
    - Rosenstiel, Annette, 1954-1971; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 14)
    - Rosenthal, Elizabeth C, 1948-1955; 1 folder (Box 157, Folder 15)
    - Rosenthal, Elizabeth C, 1957-1964; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 1)
    - Rossin, Alice H, 1940-1948; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 2)
    - Ruark, Robert C, 1948; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 3)
    - Runkle, Scott F, 1958; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - Rural Coalition, 1986; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 5)
    - Russell, Charles, 1940-1956; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 6)
    - Russell Sage Foundation, 1946-1948; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 7)
    - Russell Tribunal, 1980; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 8)
    - Sackler, Elizabeth, 1992; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 9)
    - Sadler, James H, 1990-1991; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 10)
    - Samuel H. Kress Foundation, 1952-1953; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 11)
    - Sandoz, Mari, 1950-1960; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 12)
    - Sanitation, 1961-1968; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 13)
    - Save the Children Federation, 1948-1986; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 14)
    - Savit, Christina, 1992; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 15)
    - Scalping, 1950-1951; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 16)
    - Scanlon, Tom, 1978; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 17)
    - Schiffman, Harold, 1987; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 18)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur M. Sr, 1959; 1 folder (Box 158, Folder 19)
    - Scott, Jane E, 1985; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 1)
    - Scott, Kenneth R, 1987; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 2)
    - Scottsdale National Indian Arts Council, 1973-1975; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 3)
    - Screen Actors Guild, 1993; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 4)
    - Seaton, Fred A, 1958-1960; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 5)
    - Seattle Foundation, 1955; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 6)
    - Segundo, Thomas A, 1952-1955; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 7)
    - Self-Government, 1942-1958; 1989; 1993; 3 folders (Box 159, Folder 8-10)
    - Senungetuk, Joseph, 1968; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 11)
    - Seven States Indian Health Association, 1976; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 12)
    - Seventh Generation Fund, 1985-1989; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 13)
    - Sexton, Helen R, 1957; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 14)
    - Shannon, Mary Lou, 1977; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 15)
    - Shapiro, Rebecca D, 1977-1978; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 16)
    - Shell Companies Foundation, 1976-1989; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 17)
    - Sheltering Arms Childrens Services, 1977-1979; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 18)
    - Sheridan, Henry and Nina, 1949-1950; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 19)
    - Shiya, Thomas S, 1959-1961; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 20)
    - Showell, Jacqueline, 1985-1987; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 21)
    - Siblings Rights, 1976-1977; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 22)
    - Sidney Hillman Foundation, 1950; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 23)
    - Simon, John, 1977-1982; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 24)
    - Singer, Beverly, 1988; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 25)
    - Slagle, Allogan, 1988-1989; 1 folder (Box 159, Folder 26)
    - Slagle, Allogan, 1989-1994; 2 folders (Box 160, Folder 1-2)
    - Smart, Leta Myers, 1966; 1 folder (Box 160, Folder 3)
    - Smart, S. Bruce, Jr, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 160, Folder 4)
    - Smead Foundation, 1994; 1 folder (Box 160, Folder 5)
    - Smeal, Henry F, 1990-1993; 1 folder (Box 160, Folder 6)
    - Smith, Corinna Lindon, 1928-1935; 1953-1965; 2 folders (Box 160, Folder 7-8)
    - Smith, Eva Marie, 1974-1975; 1 folder (Box 160, Folder 9)
    - Smithson, Thomas L, 1970-1971; 1 folder (Box 160, Folder 10)
    - Smithsonian Institution, 1921; 1984-1993; 2 folders (Box 160, Folder 11-12)
    - Sneve, Virginia Driving Hawk, 1971-1975; 1 folder (Box 160, Folder 13)
    - Snyder, Gary, 1974; 1 folder (Box 160, Folder 14)
    - Social Security, 1946-1962; 1971-1981; 2 folders (Box 161, Folder 1-2)
    - Social Services, 1974-1977; 1980-1991; 3 folders (Box 161, Folder 3-5)
    - Society for Applied Anthropology, 1952-1956; 1 folder (Box 161, Folder 6)
    - Society for the Preservation of American Indian Culture, 1985; 1 folder (Box 161, Folder 7)
    - Sohappy, David, 1990; 1 folder (Box 161, Folder 8)
    - Solenberger, Robert R, 1943-1945; 1 folder (Box 161, Folder 9)
    - Solstice Project (Formerly Anasazi Project), 1978-1983; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 1)
    - Soto, Peter, 1975; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 2)
    - South American Indians, 1970-1980; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 3)
    - Southwest Indian Alcoholism Council, 1965-1968; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 4)
    - Southwestern Indian Polytechnic Institute, 1993; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 5)
    - Speakers, 1948-1959; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 6)
    - Stackpole Company, 1959; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 7)
    - Stanford Research Institute, 1954-1955; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 8)
    - Statute of Limitations, 1982-1983; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 9)
    - Steele-Reese Foundation, 1958-1964; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 10)
    - Steelhead Trout, 1980-1981; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 11)
    - Stein, Wayne J, 1990; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 12)
    - Sterilizations, 1968-1978; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 13)
    - Stern, Milton, 1968; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 14)
    - Sternberg, Martin S, 1989; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 15)
    - Stevens, Alden, 1952-1968; 1 folder (Box 162, Folder 16)
    - Stevens, Marion, 1968-1987; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 1)
    - Stevens, Theodore F, 1961-1965; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 2)
    - Stevenson, Adlai E, 1955-1961; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 3)
    - Stevenson, Gelvin, 1987; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 4)
    - Stiffarm, Lenore A, 1986; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 5)
    - Stoddard, Frances B, 1955-1957; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 6)
    - Stone, Veda W, 1979-1980; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 7)
    - Stoneback, L.E., 1958; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 8)
    - Street, Eloise, 1954-1955; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 9)
    - Suffrage, 1948-1958; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 10)
    - Suicide, 1969; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 11)
    - Sulzberger, Arthur Ochs, 1958-1970; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 12)
    - Sulzberger, Iphigene Ochs, 1951-1962; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 13)
    - Summit III Conference of the Dakota-Lakota-Nakota Nations Unification Accord, 1991; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 14)
    - Surdna Foundation, 1994; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 15)
    - Survival International, 1980; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 16)
    - Swanson, W. O, 1954-1955; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 17)
    - Swearingen, Noble J, 1956-1964; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 18)
    - Swimmer, Ross O, 1987-1988; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 19)
    - Taconic Foundation, 1963-1964; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 20)
    - Tanenbaum, Joan S, 1990; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 21)
    - Tarrell, Dorothy, 1958; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 22)
    - Tax, Sol, 1952-1962; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 23)
    - Taxation, 1952-1987; 1 folder (Box 163, Folder 24)
    - Taylor, Michael N, 1977-1988; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 1)
    - Teich, Howard, 1986; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 2)
    - Termination of Federal Responsibilities, 1952-1970; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 3)
    - Thanksgiving, 1987; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 4)
    - Thompson, Thomas A, 1983-1987; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 5)
    - Thunder Hawk, Adelbert, 1953-1954; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 6)
    - Topedo, Frieda Jo, 1979; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 7)
    - Toubbeh, Jamil I, 1987; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 8)
    - Trachoma, 1961-1970; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 9)
    - Tracy, 1971 June; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 10)
    - Trade with Indians, 1972; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 11)
    - Traditional Circle of Indian Elders and Youth, 1992; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 12)
    - "Trail of Broken Treaties", 1972; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 13)
    - Treaties, undated; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 14)
    - Tribal Bonds, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box 164, Folder 15)
    - Tribal Codes and Constitutions, 1958-1990; 2 folders (Box 164, Folder 16-17)
    - Tribal Colleges, 1991; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 1)
    - Tribal Leaders, 1952-1958; 1969-1992; 2 folders (Box 165, Folder 2-3)
    - Tribal Managers Corps, undated; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 4)
    - Tribal Reorganization Regulations, 1961; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 5)
    - Tribal Sovereignty Program, 1980; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 6)
    - Trope, Jack F, undated; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 7)
    - Trudell, Richard, 1990; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 8)
    - Trust Lands Income, 1986-1988; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 9)
    - Trust Lands Status, 1952-1953; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 10)
    - Turner Broadcasting System, 1994; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 11)
    - Turshen, Meredeth, 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 12)
    - Udall, Stewart, 1960-1961; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 13)
    - Ultraviolet Germicidal Device, 1971-1974; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 14)
    - Under Baggage, Philip, 1989-1990; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 15)
    - Underhill, Ruth, 1951-1952; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 16)
    - Understanding Crow, Asa, 1952; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 17)
    - Unger, Steven, 1984-1985; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 18)
    - Unitarian Fellowship for Social Justice, 1952-1953; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 19)
    - Unitarian Service Committee, 1951-1959; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 20)
    - United American Indians, 1952; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 21)
    - United Andean Indian Mission, 1968-1969; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 22)
    - United Automobile, Aircraft and Agriculture Implement Workers of America, 1952; 1 folder (Box 165, Folder 23)
    - United Indian Development Association, 1982-1987; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 1)
    - United Indian Traders Association, 1931-1934; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 2)
    - United National Indian Tribal Youth, 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 3)
    - United Nations, 1948-1954; 1980-1993; 2 folders (Box 166, Folder 4-5)
    - United Press Associations, 1958; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 6)
    - United South and Eastern Tribes, 1980; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 7)
    - United Southeastern Tribes, 1969-1975; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 8)
    - U.S. Bicentennial, 1974-1975; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 9)
    - United Tribes for Reservation Youth, 1985; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 10)
    - United Tribes of Kansas and Southeast Nebraska, 1975-1976; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 11)
    - University of Chicago, 1952-1957; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 12)
    - University of Iowa, 1993; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 13)
    - University of Montana, 1992; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 14)
    - University of South Dakota, 1957-1962; 1 folder (Box 166, Folder 15)
    - Uranium, 1973-1983; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 1)
    - Urban Indian Health Association, 1977; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 2)
    - Urban Indians, 1970-1972; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 3)
    - Useem, John, 1947; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 4)
    - Van de Mark, Dorothy, 1954-1958; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 5)
    - Van Pelt, John A, 1953; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 6)
    - Van Sandt, M.M., 1951; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 7)
    - Venegas, Hildreth, 1989; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 8)
    - Vicary Foundation, 1987-1992; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 9)
    - Vietnam Era Veterans Inter-Tribal Association and Agent Orange, 1985-1990; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 10)
    - Vista Volunteers, 1973; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 11)
    - Vital Issues, 1953-1972; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 12)
    - Vitality Products Corporation, 1986; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 13)
    - Vocational Education, 1981-1982; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 14)
    - Vocu, Leo W, 1958-1986; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 15)
    - Vogt, Evon Z, 1952-1956; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 16)
    - Volunteers, 1991-1993; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 17)
    - Walker, Dale, 1986-1987; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 18)
    - Waln, Clyde, 1958-1961; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 19)
    - Walsh, Phyllis J, 1962-1967; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 20)
    - Walton, Phillip, 1990; 1 folder (Box 167, Folder 21)
    - Warder, Kate C, 1954-1958; 1 folder (Box 168, Folder 1)
    - Wardship, 1953-1954; 1 folder (Box 168, Folder 2)
    - Warne, William E, 1948-1950; 1 folder (Box 168, Folder 3)
    - Washburn, Mabel C, 1942; 1 folder (Box 168, Folder 4)
    - Washington Post, 1951-1958; 1 folder (Box 168, Folder 5)
    - Wassaja, 1983; 1 folder (Box 168, Folder 6)
    - Water Rights, 1950-1977; 3 folders (Box 168, Folder 7-9)
    - Water Rights, 1977-1984; undated; 2 folders (Box 169, Folder 1-2)
    - Watt, James G, 1980-1983; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 3)
    - Wayne, John, 1979; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 4)
    - Weithron, Stanley S, 1987; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 5)
    - Wellesley College, 1953-1962; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 6)
    - West Point, 1981; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 7)
    - Westermeyer, Joseph, 1972-1979; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 8)
    - Western Electric Fund, 1970; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 9)
    - Wheelwright, Mary C, 1933-1953; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 10)
    - White, Amelia Elizabeth, 1928-1936; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 11)
    - White Buffalo Calf Woman Society, 1982; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 12)
    - White, Edward A, 1985; 1 folder (Box 169, Folder 13)
    - White House and Related Correspondence, 1953-1956; 1 folder (Box 170, Folder 1)
    - White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1950-1970; 1 folder (Box 170, Folder 2)
    - White Shirt, Reba A, 1991; 1 folder (Box 170, Folder 3)
    - White, William L, 1953-1959; 1 folder (Box 170, Folder 4)
    - Whitman, Muriel E, 1975; 1 folder (Box 170, Folder 5)
    - Whittier, Maude J, 1961-1963; 1 folder (Box 170, Folder 6)
    - Wieting, Frederick C, 1963; 1 folder (Box 170, Folder 7)
    - Wilder, LeRoy W, 1980-1983; 1 folder (Box 170, Folder 8)
    - Wilderness Society, 1990-1993; 2 folders (Box 170, Folder 9-10)
    - William C. Whitney Foundation, 1940-1966; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 1)
    - William H. and Mattie Wattis Harris Foundation, 1977-1984; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 2)
    - William S. Paley Foundation, 1941; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 3)
    - Willimantic State Teachers College, 1952; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 4)
    - Wilson, Edmund, 1959; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 5)
    - Wilson, Roberta M, 1986; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 6)
    - Wirt, Emmet, 1933-1935; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 7)
    - Wisdom of the Elders Project, 1993; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 8)
    - W.K. Kellog Foundation, 1957; 1994; 2 folders (Box 171, Folder 9-10)
    - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1951-1953; 1993; 2 folders (Box 171, Folder 11-12)
    - Wood, Cornelius A, 1951-1953; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 13)
    - Woodenlegs, John, 1968-1982; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 14)
    - Woodrow Wilson Foundation, 1952; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 15)
    - Woods Charitable Fund, 1987; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 16)
    - Woolman, Barbara, 1950-1951; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 17)
    - Working Indians Civil Association, 1969-1974; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 18)
    - World Almanac Publications, 1984-1985; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 19)
    - World's Fair: Brussels, 1958; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 20)
    - World's Fair: New York, 1939; 1 folder (Box 171, Folder 21)
    - Wortis, Ethel E, 1966-1991; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 1)
    - Wounded Knee Occupation and Subsequent Unrest, 1973-1975; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 2)
    - WQXR (New York), 1965-1967; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 3)
    - Wyomissing Foundation, 1955-1956; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 4)
    - Yankton, Andreau M, undated; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 5)
    - Yellow Robe, Evelyn, 1951; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 6)
    - Yellowrobe, Rosebud, 1951-1955; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 7)
    - Yellowtail, Robert, 1954; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 8)
    - Yoder, Charles A, 1967-1970; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 9)
    - Young Men's Christian Association, 1959; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 10)
    - Young, Viola, 1948-1949; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 11)
    - Young, Wathene, 1992-1993; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 12)
    - Young Women's Christian Association, 1952-1957; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 13)
    - Zimmerman, William Jr, 1954-1957; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 14)
    - Zuern, Ted, undated; 1 folder (Box 172, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 2: Tribal, 1852-1994; 120 boxes
    All records in Series 2, Subseries 2 are open for reseach use.
    Series 2: Subject Files, Subseries 2: Tribal (1852-1994), the single largest body of material in the collection, documents the AAIA's relationship with more than 300 Native American communities and organizations from one end of the country to the other and the matters of uppermost concern to them. The AAIA's involvement in the lives of these entities varied widely in duration and intensity, sometimes precipitated by natural or man-made crises, sometimes engendered by long-term but equally invidious threats to tribal self-sufficiency. Many critical junctures in Native American history are chronicled in this subseries, from the Pueblo of Taos' struggle to recover its sacred Blue Lake to the Native Village of Point Hope's opposition to nuclear detonations; from the termination of Wisconsin's Menominee to the recognition of Florida's Miccosukee. Less prominent but, to the communities concerned, vitally important issues abound in these files, be it the location of a high school, the consolidation of two Indian agencies, the preservation of traditional fishing rights, or the encroachment of a hydroelectric project.
    This subseries is composed mainly of correspondence but also includes such items as reports, clippings, and minutes.
    The correspondence is extremely varied, with many exchanges between Native American leaders and the AAIA's executive directors. The former spoke not only for tribes but for umbrella groups such as the Alaska Federation of Natives, the Association of Village Council Presidents, the Cook Inlet Native Association, the Eight Northern Indian Pueblos Council, the Inter Tribal Council of Arizona, the Inuit Circumpolar Conference, and the Tanana Chiefs Conference, to name the organizations most strongly represented here. Other correspondence takes the form of exchanges internal to the AAIA, including ever important communications between its office in New York and its field workers, general counsel, and, during his years in New Mexico, its president, Oliver La Farge, as it endeavored to craft a response to various tribal needs. Exchanges with the Bureau of Indian Affairs and other governmental and nongovernmental entities can also be found. An important supplement to the correspondence in this subseries is offered by various tribal documents, among them constitutional and administrative records, and reports and surveys prepared or assembled by the AAIA in its efforts to inform itself and others about the situation of Native Americans.
    If this subseries has an overriding strength, it is its capacity to reveal the diversity and commonality of the American Indian experience. While, for example, the erection of massive dams and the concomitant loss of tribal patrimony was a recurring theme, the racial discrimination faced by Indians such as Louisiana's Houma and North Carolina's Lumbee had a distinctively segregationist stamp. If there is evidence of Native American cohesion in intertribal organizations such as the United Tribes of North Dakota or the Kumeyaay Tribal Council, there is also evidence of disunity, as in the case of the Osage, where a restricted franchise was bitterly contested, or in the case of the long-running territorial dispute between the Navajo and Hopi. The role of the AAIA was also variable, containing programmatic elements, as evidenced by broad initiatives in such fields as community development and child welfare, as well as innumerable actions shaped by local circumstances. The AAIA fostered change in modest ways -- a small grant here, a small grant there -- as well as through dramatic interventions, such as its defense of Arizona's Havasupai, the "Prisoners," to use its words, "of the Grand Canyon." As this subseries attests, the Association's views did not necessarily prevail -- its failure to halt the construction of the Kinzua Dam on the Allegheny River is a case in point -- nor could it devote its energies in equal measure to all tribes. Yet, from its limited beginnings in the Southwest, the AAIA developed an ever widening interest in the fate of Native Americans, leaving not only a legacy of concrete accomplishments but a paper trail which documents the evolving fortunes and the growing self-assurance of the communities it served.